Stanford University.
Let's go back. I think we were in the
midst
of me trying to explain to you
how string theory
gives a rough explanation of the entropy
of black holes.
But there was a puzzle, if you remember,
and I'll just remind you if you didn't
remember.
Um
Let's write some equations on the
blackboard here which will be useful.
Did I draw that? I didn't draw that, did
I?
I don't think so.
Question on counting strings,
do you distinguish between the
characteristic the character of the
small strings or do you treat them as as
indistinguishable?
We treat them as indistinguishable.
And do you count Well, we treat them as
Wait, we treat them as as
indistinguishable if they're identical.
Identical length. Yeah. Yeah. And do you
count their positions within the box or
are you assuming Count their positions
within the box. Yeah. Yeah. But we're
putting them into a box of a certain
size, namely the size
that the single big string would take
up.
Yeah.
If we Well, okay, I think that that
that'll have to do.
Um
Okay, I want to
first write some equations on the
blackboard
to remind you they're simple equations
and then I want to set the target goal
for the simple little derivation of the
entropy of a black hole. It's kind of
indirect and it's very subtle but very
easy.
Doesn't it doesn't involve anything as
complicated.
I don't think it involves even a
derivative
let alone an integral.
Certainly no infinite sums.
Uh it's pretty easy.
But still, it is subtle. Sometimes the
subtlest things are the easiest ones in
the sense of easy mathematically.
Uh and this is one of them.
All right, let's write first first
equation.
G. G is Newton's constant.
We're going to work in units in which c
equals h bar equals 1. I'm not going to
set Newton's constant equal to 1. We'll
leave that floating.
All right. So c is 1 because Why is c 1?
Because we measure space and time in the
same units.
And so the speed of light is 1. Planck's
constant being equal to 1, that's
something uh that's permissible to do.
And um it's just units
in which the uncertainty principle
says that the product of the uncertainty
of position times the uncertainty of
momentum is equal to one unit, one unit
of something. Namely one unit of action,
but uh c equals h bar equals 1. But we
won't fiddle around or try to simplify
Newton's uh constant for a moment.
If Oh.
If you set c equals h bar equal to 1,
then there's only one unit that you have
to specify.
You can either take it to be a length or
a mass.
And a mass is an inverse length.
A mass is an inverse length. I'll just
remind you why that is.
It's the fact that energy, which is the
same as mass,
uh you All you need to do is to write an
equation, find some equation
uh for energy and look at the various
dimensions and we'll see what happens.
All right, so energy, for example, in
quantum mechanics,
energy is given by Planck's constant
uh divided by the wavelength
times c.
Where lambda is the wavelength of a
photon, for example. This would be a uh
connection between the energy of a
photon and its wavelength. We're not
using it for anything except to say what
the relationship between the energy uh
between the
mass units and length units are.
Now, this is not the mass. To make it
mass, I think we have to divide it by c
squared. Is that right? E over c squared
is equal to m.
There were lots of people who knew that
e over c squared was equal to m, but it
took the genius of Einstein to realize
that m is equal to c squared.
True.
All right, so we put another c in here,
a c downstairs.
But I don't really care. Now this is m.
I don't really care where the c's are
because we're going to set them equal to
1.
So
the only point of this
was to say the units of mass
when we set c equal to 1 are the same as
the units of Planck's constant over
length. But if we also set Planck's
constant equal to 1,
then the units of mass are one over
length. So keep that in mind. Mass is
one over length.
In units, unit-wise.
Okay?
Now, what about the units of g? We have
not set g equal to 1. G has units. It's
not too hard to figure out what the
units of of g are. We just take again
some equation that has g in it.
And uh we look at its uh What's the
simplest equation that contains g?
Uh acceleration equals mass times g over
r squared.
Good. Acceleration
equals g
m
over r squared. Now, the left-hand side,
what's the units of the left-hand side?
l over t squared
m over t squared
You need the uh
Is length over time squared?
But length and time have the same units
when c is equal to 1.
So
this is just length over length squared,
which is one over length, right?
R squared, of course, is length squared.
So let's call this length squared.
And now we can multiply both sides of
the equation by length squared.
And this becomes length upstairs.
Ooh, we knew that before, didn't we?
That's the radius This is the
Schwarzschild radius or
proportional to the Schwarzschild radius
of a black hole.
But now, a mass is one over a length.
Inverse length.
And so we can write that the mass
is one over a length,
transfer it to the other side,
and we discover that in these units,
g
has units of an area.
What area?
There's only one area around
uh that it could be. It's the Planck
area.
All right, so g is in fact not only
an area,
it's also
the Planck area squared.
It's an important equation.
And in fact, that helps us understand
why it is that the entropy of a black
hole is the area divided by 4 * g.
Forget the 4. It's the area divided by
g. It's the area in Planck units is what
it is.
Okay, so that's one equation.
Now,
there's another fact, and that's that g,
of course, also has It's not just a
length squared. It does have to do with
the strength of gravity.
Okay, so let's think about it
in the context of string theory as
having to do with the force of gravity.
What does the force of gravity come
from? The force of gravity and
no explanation of this tonight. This is
not for tonight. We've talked about it
before. This is just a a cartoon.
The force of gravity between two
objects, this could be the Earth, this
could be the Moon over here, is due to
the exchange of gravitons.
How does that happen in string theory?
Well, everything is made up out of
strings.
A little string breaks off. How does it
break off? It breaks off
when the string crosses itself.
There is a probability
that when a string
Can everybody see this string?
When it Oh boy, I
No, let's see. We want to turn this hand
around, keep that hand stay Yeah, okay.
When the string crosses itself, that it
can rearrange.
All right? That when the string crosses
itself, that it can rearrange. That
probability, or the square root of that
probability, strictly speaking, square
root of it, is called the amplitude for
string
rearrangement or string breaking or
whatever. No, it's not really breaking.
It's rearrangement. And it's called
little g. We've talked about it before.
Little g.
The main thing about it is it's a proba-
it's a square root of a probability, and
a probability
has no units. So it's dimensionless.
There's little g, which is the
probability that when a string crosses
itself, it breaks off a little piece.
That little piece
jumps across
to another thing,
rearranges again,
so that the string jumps from one side
to the other. That in string theory is
the Feynman diagram, or the analog of
the Feynman diagram, which has to do
with the forces between the two sides.
And the important thing is that it's
proportional to two powers of this G.
One
to emit the little string and one to
absorb the little string.
That tells us the force of gravity is
proportional to little G squared.
All right. So, what it must tell us then
is that
little G squared
must be proportional to Newton's
constant.
Newton's constant is the strength of
gravity.
Little G
is the probability for break of string
breaking. But, this can't be right.
The left-hand side is dimensionless, has
no dimensions, it's just a probability.
The right-hand side has units of area.
So, there has to be something else in
here
to make up the units
to give you an area on the left side.
What is that?
That has to do with the fundamental
length scale of string theory. It's not
the Planck length.
It's the fundamental length square
length scale of string theory.
It is basically, if you look at a long
wiggly string,
you'll discover
inevitably it consists of little
wiggles, it random walks, but it has
little wiggles. And it's basically the
size of the little wiggles.
Basic size of the little wiggles
are and it's called L string.
We've talked about it before, but I'm
just reminding you.
It's the only other variable around in
the problem. This is L Planck squared.
This side is string theory.
This side is gravity.
Gravity tells us that this side is L
Planck squared.
The only sensible equation that I can
write that only contains things that
have to do with string theory on this
side
is to say that this is G squared
times L string squared. And that's the
correct equation.
That is the correct equation that
the Planck length squared, which is the
same as big G,
is little G squared times L string
squared. Now, just think about what that
means.
That means that
if little G
were tiny, a tiny number,
gravity would be very weak.
And what it would tell us is that the
Planck length was much, much smaller
than the string length.
So, in fact, this G, this little G,
which appears here,
can also be thought of as having to do
with the relative size of the Planck
length scale, the length scale that has
to do with gravity, and the string
length scale.
In fact, we can even take the square
root of this equation.
Let's do so.
It says
that L Planck is G times L string.
Okay. So, that's another equation I want
to write down here.
L Planck
is equal to G
times L string.
What other equations do we need?
All right. Next equation.
Just make a list of them
before we try to use them and before we
try to derive anything.
Next equation, the entropy of a string.
The entropy of a string, S.
Now, remember, entropy basically counts
the number of decisions, yes, no, or up,
down, or left, right decisions
that you have to make to describe a
system. Let's just leave it at that.
It's the number of primitive
binary
doesn't matter what's binary, it could
be trinary
uh
or quaternary or some small number,
number of decisions that you have to
make to specify a configuration.
I gave you a little example
of a model for string theory. And it is
a it's a reasonably good model for
string theory. It's one that statistical
mechanics people use all the time, not
for string theory, but for other
purposes,
where they replace a string
by a series of links of a lattice
and so forth.
Link can go back on itself, can do
whatever it wants.
All right.
Depending on the number of dimensions of
space,
let's just be simple and and think about
two dimensions of space for simplicity.
Then, the string, whenever it gets to a
new vertex, has a choice that it can
make of moving
further in any of four directions. All
right. So, it's not it's not binary,
it's uh
each decision
requires two
binary decisions.
Uh
the binary decisions could Well, you if
you have four possibilities, that's
equivalent to two um
uh to two heads, tails kind of
decisions.
Let's not distinguish worry about
difference between four and two.
The number of
elementary decisions to describe the
configuration of the string is clearly
proportional to its length.
All right.
So, the entropy of a string
is
the number of decisions
is going to be proportional
to the length of the string. Let me not
write it that way. Let me write it not
L, but not the string length,
but the length of the string. Let's just
call it L.
And
uh
But, that's not a consistent equation.
Why not?
Entropy is dimensionless.
Entropy has no units.
At least in modern statistical
mechanics, where uh
we're familiar with the idea that
entropy is really energy.
Uh ent-
No, entropy is not Temperature is
energy.
Um entropy has no units. Length has
units. So, this equation can't be right.
The problem with the equation is it's
not telling us how long each one of
these little excursions is.
We're talking roughly about a random
walk.
And in order to talk about a random
walk, you have to talk about the the the
size scale of the individual steps of
the random walk.
These are the steps of the random walk.
And guess what? The size of the steps of
a random walk for a string is L string.
So,
the natural thing is to count up how
many
wiggles are there or how many steps are
there. That's going to be the length of
the string
divided by L string.
All right.
That's the uh that's
the entropy of a string. Now, notice,
it's length divided by L string. I'm
going to write another equation for it
in a minute.
What about
the
Everybody knows, I assume, the
convention that S is entropy.
Uh I will write I'll write it just to
remind you. Entropy.
Okay. What about the mass of the string?
Well, the mass of the string is also
clearly proportional to its length.
It's just the mass of the sum of the
little bits. Now, that's a mild
oversimplification, but not much.
In the end, it's true.
Uh you might ask, "What happened to the
kinetic energy of the motion of the
string?" Well, it's it's not too hard to
prove
and using a little bit statistical
mechanics that the kinetic energy plus
the potential of the is essentially
equal to the potential energy.
Uh
It is a correct statement in the end
that the mass of the string is just the
sum
of the masses are for each one of the
little segments.
Okay.
But, what's the mass of a segment? That
leaves us with the question of what is
the mass of a segment? What is the mass
of the most primitive basic little piece
of string?
Let's call it M.
I don't
We're going to There's a bit of an
ambiguity. I'm going to write M string,
but I don't mean the mass of the whole
big string. I mean the mass of the
little bit of elementary string. Is that
of length LS? It's of It's of length of
LS.
It's of length LS. And now, all we have
to remember is that mass units are the
same as inverse length units.
Mass units are the same as inverse
length units.
And the only possible equation that we
can write down for this
is that it's equal to 1 divided by the
string length scale.
So, whatever the string length scale is,
there's associated with it, the smaller
it is, the bigger the mass scale.
So,
if the basic unit of length for a string
is 10 to the minus six zillion
centimeters,
then the mass of a little bit of string
is going to be 10 to the plus six
zillion something or others.
All right. So, the smaller the string
length, the bigger the mass scale.
And now we can write down the answer.
The mass of the string, the total mass
of the string
is equal
to the number of little segments. How
many little segments? The number of
The number of little segments
is L divided by L string
times the mass of each
little segment. And that gives us
another L string downstairs.
We can minute This is the mass of the
big string. Let's call this the mass big
M
stands for the whole thing. Now we can
manipulate these equations in various
ways. We can also write this as the
length of the string
times
little m sub string
because L string in the denominator is
the same as m string in the numerator
and so forth and so on. Oh, we can do a
bit more.
We can get rid of L
by replacing it with M.
Let's replace it by M. Let's just
write some more equations.
Doing nothing here. L is L string
squared times capital M.
So what is that going to give us? That's
going to give us
uh
L string
squared times capital M.
That's L
times M string. But M string is one over
L string, right?
So we can just take away one of these L
strings.
I think I'll just condense this into two
equations because parts of them are not
interested in.
S
is the length divided by the string
length
but it also happens to be the mass times
the string length.
The total mass of the total string M
times the string length.
Okay. Now I want to compare some of
these equations with black hole physics.
I don't think I need this. Write it
down. I may need it again, but I don't
think so. But let's Maybe I will, maybe
I won't.
This is string theory if you like.
All right.
I should have headed the column here
string theory.
String theory.
Okay. Now let's put over here black hole
theory
which we can also call gravitational
theory or general relativity
but a little more than general
relativity. General relativity plus
Hawking and Bekenstein who taught us
about the entropy of black holes.
All right. So here we put black hole
physics.
Uh
This of course is part of it, but I'm
mainly interested in the entropy of a
black hole.
The entropy of the black hole according
to Bekenstein
is equal to the area of the horizon
A
divided by
either L Planck squared. Let's write it
as L Planck squared
or capital G. Either one. And I'm going
to
They're the same thing, so I'm not
I'm not cheating you or anything. Area
and there's there's there's a numerical
coefficient. Do you remember what the
numerical coefficient was?
Four.
Four. We're never going to be able to
calculate that four. It's too hard. It's
but this is the this is the scaling.
This is the parametric behavior of it.
The area divided by L
Planck squared.
Compare that
with this equation over here.
The entropy is the length in string
units. It's the
another system.
Length
divided by string length
for strings
area divided by Planck area for black
holes.
Now, I'm not saying these are the same.
They're not the same. They're clearly
not the same. I'm just pointing out the
similarities and the differences.
We can also
write this another way.
The area
is equal to the square of the
Schwarzschild radius
and the Schwarzschild radius is MG.
Now I'm leaving out twos and fours and
things like that.
MG is the Schwarzschild radius.
We want to square that. M squared G
squared. That's the area.
And now we want to divide it
by either G or L Planck squared. Let's
divide it by G.
It's L Planck squared.
And it's just M squared times G.
M squared times G
and G is L Planck squared. So we can
rewrite this as just
M squared
L Planck squared.
That's the entropy.
Write it over here.
No, there it is.
Let's get rid of this. Yeah.
All right. So again, there's a
similarity and a difference.
The similarity is
mass of some power of mass sometimes
some power of Planck length
being
different and similar to some power of
mass times some power of string length.
Okay. So
Let me write it over here. Equals
M squared L Planck squared.
What if anything is the connection
between these formulas? Is there any
connection? Are they in any way the
same? Clearly they're not the same.
If a string is
If a string is a black hole and a black
hole is a string and what else could a
black hole be in string theory but a
string?
There isn't nothing in string theory
except strings.
So if a black hole is a string
it would stand to reason that it should
satisfy some rules of string theory. And
you might think this is the right
formula.
But
this is
missing something important. It's
missing
the
strong interactions
between the parts of the string, namely
the gravitational interactions between
it
which have an effect of squeezing the
string together.
We haven't accounted for that. We
haven't accounted
uh it's almost like pretending The
mistake we're making is something like
this.
If we wanted to calculate the properties
of a star
of a given mass and a given temperature
uh we might take
that amount of mass and put it in a box
about as big as a star
that amount of particles
uh no, put them in a box. Don't put them
in a box as big as a
Put them in a box bigger than the size
of the star.
And
heat the box up
to the temperature of the star.
Would that be a good description of the
star?
No, it wouldn't be a good description of
the star. It would leave out one
important thing, the gravitational
forces between the parts of the star
which pull it together, make the size of
the box smaller than it would be
smaller than it would be for the same
gas at the same temperature at the same
entropy and so forth.
Uh
And in fact, change the relationship
between entropy and energy.
It changes the relationship between
entropy and energy because it changes
the energy of the star.
In fact, the energy of the star is less
than it would be if it wasn't for
gravity. It's less than it would be
because the forces pulling it together
are attractive and the pulling it
together lowers the energy.
So you have to account for that. We have
to account for the
complicated physics of what pulls the
string together and turns it in
to this tiny tiny little nugget of a
black hole.
And of course, actually following that
is difficult. Yeah. Yeah, just to
combine the two
um
blackboards together.
You have a a string with uh
big L over L sub S
lengths and then you said the if
if a little piece of it breaks off, then
the entropy is less.
But the total entropy of the system
It would be It would be It would be less
than the I didn't say that, but Did I
say that? I don't think so.
That's what this
where you had one big string and then
three little
Oh, oh, oh, oh. Yeah.
If you broke it up into pieces
uh in the same volume, the entropy would
be less. So so you have a big string and
then a little chunk sort of goes off and
that's called a graviton. It does lower
the entropy a little bit. So that's my
question is It does. Does it the gravity
the
gravitating process lower the entropy?
No.
No. No, it actually doesn't. Um no more
than it lowers the mass of the
the
the particles which jump back and forth
between the uh the virtual particles
which jump back and forth between the
Sun and the Earth
form a kind of equilibrium
and the equilibrium neither increases
nor decreases the mass of the Sun in
itself. So So when a graviton gets
absorbed, it makes the string bigger and
that cancels out.
Yeah, but then another one another one
jumps the other way.
Let's just leave it at that. An
equilibrium is set up and uh
we're not going to do quantum field
theory tonight. As I said, the picture
of things jumping back and forth, the
cartoon, is too simple uh uh
for a real discussion. All we really
used it for
was to say
that capital G was proportional to
little g squared and that I assure you
is is uh
is true.
Okay.
Now, we're going to make a hypothesis or
a guess.
And the guess is going to be
The first half of the guess is not a
guess.
If you take a string
and in particular, you take a string
under the circumstance that little g is
so small imagine that little g starts
out essentially zero
no probability at all for it to split
and join
that's the same as turning off the
strength of gravity
letting little g be arbitrarily small,
let's say zero
is the same as turning off gravity
altogether. Under those circumstances,
you're not turning off
you're not turning off other things
but turning off little g, sending it to
zero
produces a string which has a bunch of
wiggles in it
and it's a string for which you don't
have to worry about what happens when
the string crosses itself. It just goes
right through and nothing happens.
Okay.
That's one limit of string theory. Now,
you imagine starting to increase g,
little g.
You imagine starting to increase little
g
gravity starts turning on.
We're keeping L string fixed. The thing
we're keeping You always ask, "What are
What is he keeping What is he keeping
fixed?"
I'm keeping L string fixed. The size of
these wiggles. And now I start turning
on little g.
The Newton constant starts getting
bigger.
Gravity starts becoming important for
this object and eventually does the same
thing to it that gravity would do to the
star.
Make gravity strong enough and the star
will turn into a black hole.
Now, the interesting thing about string
theory is little g is a quantity which
can change in string theory. You can
imagine a dial which turns it. It is
It's a variable in the theory. We're not
going to get deeply into that, but it is
meaningful in string theory to change
little g.
This is what happens to a big blob of
highly excited string as you increase g.
It pulls the string together and
eventually turns it into a black hole.
What happens if you take the black hole
now
and you start decreasing g?
Eventually, you come to the point where
there's not enough gravity to hold the
string to hold the black hole together.
Eventually, you can imagine when little
g gets so small let's say zero
then there's no gravity left at all.
What can the black hole turn into?
There's only one thing around for it to
turn into in that limit, strings.
That's all there is in string theory.
If that's all there is, it has to turn
back into string.
Well, it could turn into one string, it
could turn into two strings, it could
turn into three strings, it could turn
into four strings, maybe a zillion
strings. That might be your best guess
unless you know that the overwhelming
majority of configurations was a single
string.
So, the basic guess
is that this is kind of a reversible
game.
Take a highly excited string, turn on
gravity, it turns into a black hole.
Turn off gravity, it turns back into a
string. Do it slowly.
Call it adiabatically.
String turns to black hole
back again to string and back and forth
again.
Now, the one thing about doing things
slowly
is it doesn't change the entropy.
That's a property of entropy.
In the 19th century, it was discovered
that entropy is an adiabatic invariant.
The meaning of that
an adiabatic invariant was a quantity
which doesn't change when you turn when
you change things slowly.
That was the notion of an adiabatic
invariant and it was noticed
uh
in various contexts that entropy was an
adiabatic invariant if you vary things
slowly.
So, here's the game we're going to try
to play. We're going to try to say,
"Look, let's start with a black hole.
Let's take this is our target black hole
over here.
It has mass.
Let's give it capital M for big mass.
It has mass M and let's call it M
naught.
Just to indicate it's it's The naught is
just indicating it's the one that we're
interested in.
And
there is a coupling constant g naught
so that gravity is strong enough to hold
it together into a black hole.
It's an M naught and a g naught such
that it is a black hole.
And now somebody comes along and starts
turning the dial, the g dial
starts decreasing g.
Decreases g so much that gravity
effectively
turns off.
What happens to the black hole
incidentally when you start turning off
gravity? When you start decreasing the
strength of gravity? Does it grow or
does it shrink?
It grows.
It grows because after all, if you turn
gravity on, it shrinks.
Right. It starts growing
and at some point
it turns back into a string.
We're going to guess at what point that
happens. We're going to make two
guesses. They're not really guesses.
They're uh some things we could
with a little bit of mathematics, we
could confirm.
We're going to treat them as intuitive
guesses.
All right. The first
thing
has to do with the entropy of a black
hole.
I'm not going to use this formula
because that's the formula I'm going to
try to prove.
This is the The target is to prove this
formula.
That the entropy of a black hole is M
squared L Planck squared. Using the fact
that the entropy of a string
is M times L string.
That's what we're going to try to do.
Use this fact to prove this fact.
Now, these equations can't possibly You
can't You can't take these equations,
start plugging them in, and go from here
to here. It's the wrong idea.
Uh and we'll see why.
Okay, so that's the goal, to prove this
using this and using this idea that we
can go back and forth from strings to
black holes by turning on and off the
coupling constant.
Let's start with the entropy of a black
hole. Now, here's the formula.
M squared L Planck squared.
Entropy is dimensionless.
The entropy of a large black hole
what can it depend on? The question is
what can it depend on?
And of course, it can depend on the
mass.
But mass is not dimensionless. There's
nothing you can write down that involves
only the mass that could give you It
could be mass, mass squared, mass cubed,
mass 15th power. None of them work.
What must you put here in order to get a
dimensionless thing? You must put L
Planck.
Mass times L Planck.
Mass times the the length scale that's
associated with gravity. Now, we're
doing black hole physics over here. It
doesn't even know yet about string
theory. We haven't even
We're in the old days when Hawking first
Hawking and Bekenstein first discovered
the fact that the entropy that black
holes have entropy.
And you could ask at that time, "What
can the entropy depend on?"
And Hawking and Bekenstein and everybody
else would have said, "The only thing
that it could depend on is the mass
times L Planck." But that doesn't tell
you that it's mass squared times L
Planck squared. It could be mass cubed
times L Planck cubed. It could be mass
times L Planck.
This doesn't say any such thing. Or does
This doesn't
say that.
All it says is that this is the
dimensionless combination of variables
that S can depend on.
Okay. Now, let's come to the point.
Here, we're going to draw a diagram.
We're going to draw a graph. And on the
graph, we're going to plot two things.
We're going to plot G
and we're going to plot
the mass of an object.
And we're going to start over here with
a relatively large G.
Pretty large. And
I'm And the mass is not really going to
be small. It's just I need a lot of
space here.
A lot of vertical space. So, I'm going
to put the mass down here.
But, this mass is pretty big. This mass
is pretty big. Pretty big could mean
uh a solar mass. Okay? Whatever mass you
like for a black hole.
And G is also pretty big.
So, the mass is big. G is big. It's a
black hole. There's no question it's a
black hole.
Black hole and let's give it
mass M naught
and coupling G naught.
This is the target object that we want
to understand.
We want to calculate its entropy.
But, what are we going to do?
We're going to get our magician who
turns the knob of G, who starts
decreasing it.
He starts decreasing it.
We take this object. Here it is.
And we start decreasing G.
What happens to the mass as we decrease
G?
As we decrease G,
the negative gravitational energy
disappears.
So, the mass increases.
The mass increases because we're we're
deleting
the negative gravitational uh binding
energy.
And so, the mass starts to increase.
And how does it increase?
Well, if you do it slowly, the entropy
doesn't change.
All right? But, the entropy is only a
function
of mass times L Planck.
Mass times L Planck. Oh, let's write
that another way.
I told you that this is very easy.
And it's also very subtle.
It's difficult because there's a lot of
pieces. Every single piece is no more
uh
I don't even think there's anything as
complicated as multiplication and
addition in the same formula.
The worst is multiplication and
division. I don't even think we have to
use the addition sign. Certainly not the
integral or derivative. But, there are a
lot of pieces.
L Planck, what is L Planck? L Planck is
G times L string. So, let's plug that in
here. Here, we're getting Let's say
we're getting stuff for free, and we
are.
L Planck is G
times L string.
And I'm going to hold L string fixed.
We're doing string theory. We're going
to hold the string length scale fixed.
And it tells us that the entropy is a
function of the product of M and G.
For a fixed L string. Holding
Holding L string fixed is a choice of
units. If we hold L string fixed, call
it the unit of the basic unit of mass,
then the entropy is a function of the
product of M and G.
In other words,
this line here
must be the line along which M times G
is fixed.
M times G is fixed along here. Why is
it? Let me go back again.
We're slowly varying G, and so we don't
change the entropy.
But, the entropy is known to be a
function of M times G.
So, it must be that MG is fixed along
here.
MG is fixed along here.
It has to equal M naught G naught at
this point. And so, I can tell you
immediately what this curve is.
Can anybody tell me?
It's a hyperbola.
And it's a hyperbola
MG
is equal to M naught G naught.
It's a hyperbola.
The product of M and G is fixed.
And it's fixed so that at this point
over here, it has to equal M naught G
naught.
So, this is what we found.
What we find what what would be called
in statistical mechanics, we found the
isentropic line. The line in the
parameter space where the entropy is
fixed.
Or the Or the adiabat. It's sometimes
called the adiabat.
The line along which uh
entropy is fixed.
All right. That's the first
part of the cat. Now, this The second
part
is to know where we go from black hole
to string.
Where does this black hole suddenly
change its character
and turn into a
ball of string
where that we can analyze using string
theory and not have to worry about
gravity.
And I'll tell you where it happens. It
happens Imagine
It happens at the point
where the Schwarzschild radius of the
object gets smaller than the string
length scale. Here's the idea.
As you start decreasing the coupling
constant,
the compactified string that's rammed
onto this small black hole starts to
expand. It starts to expand.
It starts to expand and expand, and
eventually it gets to the point where
these curly
loops of string
are no smaller
than the Schwarzschild radius of the
black hole. At that point, the black
hole has no more meaning than just a
ball of string.
To say the Schwarzschild radius is
smaller than the string scale
wouldn't mean anything.
It's also the point at which the
at which gravity is not strong enough to
hold the string down onto the horizon.
But, it happens at the point where the
wiggles of string are about as big as
the Schwarzschild radius would be if it
did remain a black hole.
In other words, the crossover happens.
The transition between the two of them
happens. I'll write it over here. It
happens when the Schwarzschild radius
MG
becomes equal to L string.
At that point,
a black hole
whose Schwarzschild radius is smaller
than the string length scale is not a
proper black hole. It has turned into a
string.
Once that happens, we use string theory.
Okay, let's see where this is. Let's see
if we can figure out
where this is on this diagram.
What it looks like. It's also a curve.
It's also a curve.
Why is it a curve? Because it's the
curve M.
Now, big G
is little g squared
L string squared
equals L string.
Again, we're keeping L string fixed. So,
just think of it as a number.
And it becomes the curve M
G squared
equals 1 over L string.
I emphasize, the right-hand side is just
a number.
It's whatever we choose the unit for L
string. The left-hand side is M G
squared.
So, when M G squared
when G gets small enough that M G
squared is 1 over L string, all of a
sudden
it turns into a string. The black hole
turns into a string.
So, there's another curve on here.
This other curve,
M G squared equals 1 over L string, it
looks like this.
Let's see. Do I have it right?
Yeah.
Yeah, we could write it this way.
When G is very large,
this falls off like 1 over G string
squared.
So, this falls off more rapidly. So, let
me remind you what these two curves are.
One of them is just the curve of
constant entropy for a black hole.
The other is the transition point or the
transition curve where when you go from
the right side to the left side, you go
from black hole
to string.
So, if the coupling constant is small,
and what does small mean? It depends on
the mass. But, if you're to the left of
this red line,
this lump of stuff behaves like a
string. If you're to the right of it, it
behaves like a black hole.
On the line, all along the line, that's
the way that's where the entropy is
constant. Okay, so now let's follow this
black hole
and let's follow it right to the point
where it turns into a string.
And let's see if we can find out
what
the mass and coupling in particular,
what the mass and the coupling constant
are at that point where it turns into a
string. Once it turns into a string, we
can use string theory to compute its
entropy.
So far, all we know is that its entropy
is a function of mg, but we don't know
what function of mg.
All right. So let's follow the curve to
here.
There are two curve There are two
function There are two things. One of
them, let's write down both equations.
Let's write down the equations
for the two curves
which intersect at that point. One of
them is mg
equals m naught g naught.
And just to remind you again, m naught g
naught is the target object that we're
trying to understand.
And we're playing a little game which is
changing it, but let's see what we find.
That's one equation
for the black line. The equation for the
red line, I erased it, damn it. What was
it? It was m
equals 1 over l s. g squared, I think,
is equal to 1 over l string. Yeah.
Right.
Let's solve Let's solve these
simultaneously,
and I'm going to solve them
simultaneously by squaring this one.
And now dividing one by the other so
that I get rid of g.
Okay?
The point at which they cross,
maybe I should have labeled this point
and called it the starred point.
And maybe we should have called this m
star and g star.
m star and g star.
Namely, the values of m and g at the
crossover point here.
Okay, so now we just divide one by the
other.
Uh the ratio of this one here will be m
star, right?
And that's it.
And that will equal
m naught squared g naught squared
divided by l string, right?
Well, divided by m naught
1 over l.
Divided by 1 over l string.
For time l. All right, so this one
You're dividing, right? Yeah. So I get
divided by l string.
Yeah. This one has has to be l s over
here.
It better be because it's
It's on the other side, yeah. Uh
Let's see.
You're dividing the the equation by the
other equation. Yeah.
You're dividing by 1 over l s, which is
like multiplying.
Ah, okay. 1 over l s Here Here it is,
right? No. No, no, no. l s is on top.
Upstairs.
Yes.
l s, good.
Now I think we have it right.
Yeah?
Okay.
Let me multiply both sides of it by l
string.
And then we get
m naught squared
g naught squared l string squared
is equal
to m star
l string.
What is g naught squared times l string
squared?
g
g g Capital g at this point, at the
target point.
It's capital g at the point where we
were trying to investigate
the object.
So, we can write this equation as m
naught squared
times let's just call it g naught.
Whatever the Newton constant was at this
point over here.
And here is where we want to be.
Moving on here was just a trick.
But what we find
is that it's m
star namely this point over here
times
l string.
What is this over here? m star m l
string times m star. That's entropy
which doesn't change. That's the entropy
which doesn't change.
So this is
Where's Where's the equation? That's
this equation over here.
That's the entropy which doesn't change.
It's the entropy at this point,
but it's also the entropy over here.
So in particular,
it's the entropy of interest.
So, you see, here is the connection
between the two sets of ideas.
It's not that this object over here can
be thought of as a string and you use
string theory.
You slowly change it until it becomes a
string, and then you read off the
entropy from the properties of the
string at this point. And that relates m
naught squared g naught,
which is the black hole formula over
here someplace.
Relates the black hole formula at that
point
to the string formula
at that point.
All right. That was
the origin of the connection between
uh
understanding the entropies of black
holes and relating it to the properties
of strings.
There's much more sophisticated versions
of it.
This version of it was not powerful
enough
to determine the numerical constant
numerical constant of 1/4. This was much
too crude for that. Uh Why was it too
crude? Among other Among other reasons
is there was was a bit of floppiness in
exactly where this transition happens.
The transition between string and
and black hole is not
a sharp sudden transition. And even if
it were a sharp sudden transition, we
don't have the power to predict exactly
where it is. All we can do is para
give a rough estimate.
So, this technique was not powerful
enough
to pin down the factor of 1/4.
But what it was powerful enough was to
get the same kinds of formulas
for a wide wide variety of different
kinds of black hole objects, different
dimensions of space,
different things called black brains,
things called black
black holes in all different dimensions,
charged black holes, all the whole the
whole works.
The same technique worked,
but not good enough to get the numerical
factor.
The numerical factor was provided by a
very mathematically sophisticated
version
uh which had a great deal of symmetry
and super symmetry and other things that
we're not going to do.
Uh it didn't It didn't add anything
conceptually very new. It added the
power of symmetry to make very precise
computations.
And the end result was that this factor
of four
was
correctly identified.
Okay, that's so much for strings and
entropy.
But uh just to summarize it, what does
it mean?
The It doesn't mean that string theory
is correct.
It means
that a mathematically
consistent description of gravity and
quantum mechanics, which does contain
black holes, has within its own
framework an explanation of the entropy
of black holes.
Why do you need an an explanation of
entropy of black holes? Well,
um
entropy, as I've told you time and
again, is an indication of the existence
of microscopic
substructure
which your equations or your rough
coarse-grained description may not see.
So, the fact that black holes had
entropy was a evidence that there were
some underlying small structures there
describing whatever
black hole is or whatever the horizon of
a black hole is.
And um
uh
to get at it, string theory is one one
method. Oh, one other thing which is
most interesting is that the power came
out right here. It might have come out
to be m cubed l Planck cubed.
What would the interpretation of that
have been?
Notice, this is something All right,
this this
This, of course, was the main point of
this computation. That it gave the
answer Yeah. m squared l Planck squared.
It did not give m cubed l Planck cubed.
What would have been the interpretation
of m cubed l Planck cubed?
The volume.
It would have been that the entropy was
proportional to the volume of the black
hole. Right, that's what it seems like
in natural life where
you look at the cup of coffee.
Right, you look at the cup of coffee,
the entropy is proportional to the
volume. You look at a room, the entropy
is proportional to the volume.
You look at a black hole, the entropy is
proportional to the area.
And it was extremely puzzling. It still
is puzzling. This doesn't you know this
this derivation was not for the purpose
of making you feel better. It was
it uh
it had a degree of
historical value in convincing people
that the entropy of black holes really
did mean that there was a
microscopic substructure to them that
general relativity just missed.
I think I probably discussed with you
other
theories in which which are macroscopic
theories which miss the substructure
or a microscopic structure. Just
ordinary fluid dynamics. Fluid dynamics
makes use of a set of variables
which is which are averaged over many
many many particles.
The fluid flow, the fluid density
um and things like that. The temperature
of the fluid locally and um
and the fact that the fluid has entropy
was a indication that it had some kind
of additional small distance structure
that was too small to see in the
equations. Okay.
Uh I want to move on from that to the
holographic principle.
And we're only we're going to we're
going to do this very quickly.
There's
an enormous amount that came out of the
holographic principle unexpectedly to
me.
Uh but the principle itself is very
simple. It's very simple, unexpected but
but again simple doesn't even require
integrals.
And it goes like this.
The question now is not what is the
entropy of a system. The question is
what is the maximum entropy that a
system can have?
The maximum. The notion of maximum
entropy.
Now, for many systems the maximum
entropy is infinite. For many
mathematical systems that we that we
think about in mathematical physics, you
can have arbitrary amounts of entropy.
But let's let's simplify or let's
concentrate on a class of systems.
They're a class of systems which can be
described uh I suppose you would
describe them as systems that are built
out of qubits. A qubit is a yes no
description.
Uh it's a bit. It's a bit in the sense
of the bits in your computer except Q
stands for quantum. Quantum bits. All
right, but this is the Q is not the
important thing here.
Um
We could take this room and we could
subdivide it into cells
make a cubic lattice out of it.
Let's simplify the discussion and
suppose everything in the room was made
out of one kind of atom. This of course
is a false statement. Uh we're made out
of lots of different kinds of atoms, but
let's simplify it and say we're all made
up out of
um
um meat meatonium
atoms.
That's too hard to say. We're made out
of meat. We're made out of meatonium
atoms.
And
even the air is made out of meat
meatonium.
You know what I mean.
And what we're going to do is subdivide
the room into a large number of cells.
Each cell being about as big as an atom.
The only question
that we can ask about a cell is is there
an atom in it or not?
If there's an atom in it, we can paint
it black.
If there's not an atom in it, we leave
it white.
We can make up a lot of different kinds
of configurations out of this.
Uh we can make up configurations that
look like a bunch of people sitting
here.
We need to extend it so that we have a
few more elements of course to do that.
But uh
with this very simple model we can have
a room which is
complicated enough to have us sitting
here
and in which the only question that you
ask about a cell is is it filled or is
it not filled?
The number of configurations that you
can make is clearly two to the number of
cells.
And the number of cells is the volume
divided by the volume of a cell. In this
case, the volume of a cell would be the
smallest volume that would be
appropriate to the physics problem. In
this case, the physics problem being
putting atoms in or not putting atoms
in. And so we could put in the volume of
an atom here. Two to the volume over the
volume of an atom.
That's the number of different ways of
populating this room with atoms. And the
entropy is just the logarithm of this.
The entropy is the logarithm of this so
the logarithm of the natural logarithm
is the usual definition. So the
logarithm of this thing here is V
divided by VA logarithm of two.
Now, I take it back. That is not the
entropy of this room. That's the maximum
entropy.
There are no more states than that. Now,
the entropy of this room is certainly
nothing like the maximum entropy of this
room. The maximum entropy of this room
would be a configuration of the room
which was completely chaotic.
And if we put that much entropy into the
room, it would be very hot.
We are a configuration of relatively low
entropy. This is the maximum entropy
that could be in this room in this
situation. There can't be any more and
we would write that as S maximum.
There are two things to notice about it.
One of them is that it's proportional to
the volume. That may or may not be a
deep fact. The other thing is that it's
proportional to the number of
basic decisions. Let's call it the
number of degrees of freedom. Num degree
of freedom not now meaning a thing like
a coordinate or something but a yes no
binary question.
It's proportional to the number of
degrees of freedom.
And of course for this room, the number
of degrees of freedom being proportional
to the volume, it's also proportional to
the volume.
We want to ask whether this is really
a very general feature of nature that
the maximum entropy is proportional to
the volume. I will take it
that the maximum entropy is always
proportional
to the number of degrees of freedom.
That's not that's too deep to fool
around with. I mean we could fool around
with it. But that's a very very deep
idea that the entropy counts the number
of yes no questions.
Uh
we're going to ask whether it's always
the case that it's proportional to the
volume.
And in particular
in a case that includes gravity.
So here was the argument that was put
forward you know
15 years ago uh for what the maximum
entropy of a region of space is. Here's
a region of space.
Let's take it to be a sphere for
simplicity.
It can be populated with all sorts of
stuff.
Atoms or
uh
photons
elements
They may or may not form cookies.
Cookie, that's I'm going to look at
It's hard to tell the difference between
cookie my cookies and uh
planets but
um
yeah, there's a cookie.
And the question is how many
configurations are there?
What's the maximum number of distinct
states?
Here's the argument. The argument was
really really simple.
Suppose there's an entropy in there S.
And a certain amount of energy
altogether. Let's call it M.
This is the amount of entropy that's in
there. It's not the maximum entropy. It
is the entropy that's in there and it's
the mass M.
Now, I think we're entitled to assume
that the mass M is smaller than the mass
of a black hole
whose horizon would be just that big.
If there was more mass in there,
then the horizon would be bigger than
this and it would overflow the region.
So, we're asking how much entropy can be
in stuff
which doesn't overflow
the boundary of this region.
And so, we're entitled to assume then
that the mass must be less than
the mass of a black hole
whose horizon would just fill the
region.
Otherwise, as I said, if its mass were
bigger, it would overflow the region. It
would have to overflow the region.
Now, imagine that
somebody created a shell. It doesn't
matter what the shell is made out of.
It could come in from infinity.
It could be made of light. It could be
made of protons. It could be made of uh
Swiss cheese. It doesn't matter.
And that shell comes in.
It happens to have precisely enough
mass.
It has precisely enough mass that it,
together with the mass that's in there,
happens to be the mass of a black hole
which just fills that region.
We're assuming the mass is less than the
mass of that black hole.
Let's take the red shell
to have just the mass necessary
to create
so that the the sum together will form a
black hole. And now, imagine either that
it's by its own right heavy enough to
fall in
or we give it enough of a push to make
it fall in.
And it falls in
it falls in
so that it crosses
this region.
Everybody who does general relativity
will agree that at the point where it
crosses the region
such that
this is
just big enough so that the whole thing
is a black hole that it will form a
black hole.
When you pull this in, it will form a
black hole. How big will a black hole
be? The black hole will be exactly as
big
as this region. You've you've engineered
it that way. No, it's no miracle.
You've just put enough mass in that red
shell
so that it, together with the mass in
here, is just enough to make a black
hole that big.
Okay?
What is the entropy of the final
configuration? The entropy of the final
configuration is just the entropy of the
black hole that's in there.
So, we can write that What Let's call
this this S initial. S final
is
the area divided by 4G.
The area of this region.
The one thing that we can save by the by
virtue of the second law of
thermodynamics
is that the final entropy is bigger than
the initial entropy.
So, we've proved a theorem with almost
no work. We proved the theorem.
And the theorem says that the entropy in
a region of space cannot be bigger
than the entropy of a black hole which
would just barely fill the region of
space.
It cannot because you could always
create a black hole
and thereby
create an entropy, a final entropy which
would be the area over 4G.
We prove in that way that the maximum
entropy, S max
the same object we were talking about
over here
is equal to the area divided by 4G.
This is another way of saying that the
number of degrees of freedom
of a region of space, that everything
that can be described in a region of
space
is no bigger than the area of the
bounding surface of that region
measured in Planck units.
Let's call the holographic principle.
It uh
is sometimes
the
with very, very good reason.
Um
stated a little bit differently
it's stated in saying that any region of
space can be described by a collection
of degrees of freedom. Any region of
of degrees of freedom which are one per
Planck area on the boundary of the
region. It's called the holographic
principle. It was a complete surprise.
Uh
but it's now a
official part of
standard uh physics.
I'm not going to do much with it. I'm
not going to show you how it's used,
what it's what it's what it's what its
applications have been.
That would just take us too far afield.
It has
uh had had it has had very interesting
applications.
But, um
what's most interesting about it is how
different it is
than people imagined.
And just to say it again, you know, you
would think you if you can vary
something over here and you can vary
something else over here and you can
vary something else over here
that uh that because of locality that
you can make any combination of
variations and you would think the
number of variations that you can make
is proportional to the volume.
The area
of a region measured in Planck units is
vastly, vastly smaller.
This is not a small difference.
The ratio between
uh the
the uh number of Planck cells on the
boundary to the number of Planck cells
in the in the volume of the room is a
huge ratio.
Uh so, it's a
Okay, it is what it is.
Just about this. If you have a
ignoring expansion in of the universe,
if you just have a uniform uniform
density of a very large
universe, how does what happens then?
We're going to we're going to we're
going to do that. Okay.
Yeah, we're going to do that.
Is there a connection between the this
limit on the number of degrees of
freedom and
uh the uncertainty principle?
Well,
yeah.
Um
All right. So, let's uh let's talk about
such a relationship.
Well, I'm talking about All right. I
Let me I I think I'll come back to it. I
think I'll come back to it. It's
connected with something called the
ultraviolet infrared connection in which
I had intended to talk about, but I I
let's not do it now.
Um
For the moment,
that's the holographic principle and
that's all we're going to say about it
for the moment.
We'll come back to it.
All right. I want to tell you about
horizons in cosmology.
There are lots of different kinds of
things that people call horizons in
cosmology.
But, I'm really only interested in the
ones that are analogous to uh to the
horizons of black holes.
Event horizons.
Event horizons
are by definition those places which
separate
uh from where you can or cannot get a
signal uh from the other side.
Or you never can get a signal.
All right. Um
Event horizons occur
in certain kinds of cosmologies.
By certain kinds of cosmologies, that
means certain kinds of solutions of
Einstein's
field equations applied to cosmology.
We're not going to do those equations.
I'm going to just tell you what the
solutions are. We're going to talk about
solutions of Einstein's equations, but
we're not going to try to write You're
not even going to write the equations
down. We're going to write the solutions
down.
Um
Let's begin
with the most basic concept of modern
cosmology.
Namely, the metric of an expanding
universe.
Now, there are various versions of
expanding universes.
In particular, they're characterized by
the topology of space, not space-time,
but space.
Space could be closed and bounded like a
sphere, like the surface of a sphere,
not the surface of a two-dimensional
sphere, but the surface of a
three-dimensional sphere.
It could be hyperbolic, which is a kind
of space which is infinite and
negatively curved, quite the opposite of
a sphere. But, we're not going to do
either of those tonight. We're going to
assume that space is just Euclidean
space.
Now, if space is just ordinary Euclidean
space, why are we talking about uh
cosmology? Why aren't we just talking
about ordinary Euclidean space? Well, we
want to be talking about space-time.
We want to be talking about space-time,
and the space-time we're going to talk
about What What's the What's the um
the space-time analog of Euclidean
space?
You know what it's called?
Minkowski Minkowski space. Right. We're
not going to be talking about Minkowski
space.
We're going to be talking about a space
which is more complicated, an expanding
space. But if you want to think about
it, you know, the usual picture
for thinking about um
an expanding closed space
is to go down in one dimension, go down
one dimension, view space as
two-dimensional, and then think of it as
a balloon blowing up.
As a balloon blowing up with on the
balloon
little drawings, and those little
drawings are galaxies, and as the
balloon expands, the galaxies separate
from each other.
I did once try to show that to a class
by getting a big balloon.
Those Those big big things, and blow it
up and blow it up, but uh before I did,
I had marked it with this stuff.
And then
blow it up, which this was a bad mistake
cuz it eats through rubber.
Boom! Made a big bang in the room.
Now,
that's not such a good idea for um
for describing cosmology for one simple
reason.
The rubber molecules get thinned out.
And so, the properties of space
of a local patch of space
look like they're getting thinner and
thinner. I mean, one of the consequences
of that is the separation between the
molecules eventually exceeds the
the radius of the molecular forces, and
that, of course, is when the balloon
breaks, not because I painted it with
uh
uh that stuff, but because the
separation between molecules exceeds the
uh the forces, the attractive forces.
So, you got to You have to add a little
bit. You have to imagine you have a
reservoir of rubber molecules.
And as you blow up the balloon and
increase its size, every time a space
forms where the distance between
molecules begins to exceed or get close
to the distance uh characteristic of uh
the uh the molecular forces,
add another molecule in. Add it out of
your pocket. Keep doing it. And then, of
course, you can make the balloon keep
growing and growing and growing.
Uh so, all of cosmology has that aspect
to it that uh that
it's not that space is just expanding,
but in a certain sense, it's being
replenished. The sense in which it's
being replenished
is that the properties of a local region
of space don't change as the space gets
bigger and bigger. Space doesn't get
thinned out, whatever the devil that
would mean.
I'm not sure what it would mean.
Um
Good. But we're not going to be doing
closed and bounded space.
If you wanted to do the kind of space
we're talking about, what we want to
imagine is an infinite flat sheet of
rubber.
Well, an infinite flat sheet might be a
little bit too extreme. Let's just make
it a very big flat sheet.
We could imagine four people at the
corners of the sheet, and they're
pulling it out and causing it to
uniformly expand with time.
So, the sheet The flat sheet
grows.
The separation between the molecules
increases with time, and we replenish
the molecules as it expands. The
galaxies which are drawn on this surface
separate because uh the geometry is
growing.
And it's time dependent. The We could
say the distances between things is time
dependent because the space itself is uh
is stretching.
All right. Now, those words don't Those
words are nice words. Do they have
mathematical meaning? Yes, they do have
mathematical meaning.
The mathematical meaning is through the
metric.
Through the metric of space, or the
metric of space-time.
So, I'm going to write down a metric for
you.
dt squared.
This is the ds squared
= - dt squared. Now, if I were just
writing Minkowski space, I would write +
dx squared. And the x squared here
stands for dx squared + dy squared + dz
squared, which I'm not going to write
down uh
uh in general. It would be - dt squared
+ dx squared. If you wanted to put some
speeds of light in, you would put the
speed of light in uh
c squared dc dt squared + dx squared.
But I'm not going to put in the speed of
light. This would be the thing you would
normally put in. But if space were
expanding,
you would put
multiplying the space component of the
metric, let's call it dxi dxi.
This stands for dx squared + dy squared
+ dz squared. You put what's called a
scale factor
a
of t
squared.
You put a a function there of time. Now,
what's the distance between a pair of
points
separated by delta x?
Separated by distance delta x. What is
the distance between them?
Not separated by distance, separated by
coordinate interval delta x.
The distance between two such points is
not just or the square of the distance.
Let's take the square of the distance
between the two points.
It's not delta x squared. It's delta x
squared * a squared. The distance
between neighboring points
is a squared * dx squared. If it happens
to be uh fairly large interval, it'll be
delta x, not dx. But the actual distance
between the two points, let's call it d
between point one and point two.
Here's two points, one and point two.
Each one characterized by a definite
location on the x plane. Here's the x
plane.
x, y, whatever. Here's two points.
And they're separated by a coordinate
distance. Let's put them along the x
axis.
delta x. How far are they
really in proper distance? That's what
the metric tells you. That's what
metrics are for. And the answer
is
that the d is going to be delta x
* a of t.
In other words, if the two points are
fixed in the plane, in the uh in the
coordinate plane, and the plane is being
blown up by this process of putting in
more molecules, the two points will
separate, and the distance between them
will be whatever the delta x was * a of
t.
That much is uh is That That's what a
metric means.
All right. So, this is not good old
Minkowski space where the distance
between two fixed points in coordinate
space stays fixed.
It's some kind of expanding version of
space.
Let's talk about the velocity between
those two points. The velocity between
those two points
We're holding the x's fixed. All right.
So, the two points in the plane are
fixed. They don't change.
What's the velocity between the two
points?
v
1 2
Well, that's just the time derivative of
the distance between them, right? That's
the time derivative.
What's the time derivative of the
distance between them? Well, the x's are
being kept fixed. So, delta x, the
difference of the x's are fixed. That's
not time dependent. The thing that's
time dependent is a.
In case I haven't said it, a is called
the scale factor.
It's the scale factor which is time
dependent.
That's the thing we differentiate, and
so the velocity is delta x
* Let's call it a dot. Dot standing for
time derivative.
Now, let's consider the relationship
between the distance between the points
and the velocity between them.
The velocity between the two points
is given by the distance between the two
points,
but not quite.
The velocity has a dot, the distance has
a, and so, there must be an a dot
over a. a dot of t over a.
The velocity has an a dot, the distance
has an a, but otherwise, they're the
same.
So, velocity is distance * a dot over a.
Now, a dot A has a name.
It's called the Hubble constant.
All right, it's called H.
Velocity equals distance
times Hubble constant.
Why do we call it a constant? Not A over
A, A over T.
If A is a function of time
and A. can be a function of time, in
general the ratio can be a function of
time. Why do we call What do we mean
when we say that the Hubble constant is
a constant?
We don't mean that it's a constant with
respect to time.
We mean it's a constant that don't
doesn't depend on the pair of points
that you chose.
For any pair of points
at a given at a given instant of time
the relation between velocity and
distance between them is common to all
pairs of points.
And the ratio between velocity and
distance is given by A. over A, which
doesn't depend on position, but does
depend on time.
So, the Hubble constant is kind of a
little bit of a misnomer.
It's certainly not constant with respect
to time in general.
But, it is independent of the pair of
points that you're talking about.
This, of course, is Hubble's law
Hubble's
law of expansion. Velocity
uh
It's amazing that that wasn't discovered
earlier.
By a theorist in particular who was just
thinking about this
that it wound up getting discovered by
looking through telescopes. Uh
In fact, I'm not even sure it wasn't
discovered by somebody else. Somebody
may correct me. I may be I may wind up
being corrected that it was discovered
by somebody else, but I don't know.
Okay, so that's Hubble's law.
You derive that using
infinitesimals DT and etc.
Yeah, I just differentiated.
Now, if you're talking about distance
between galaxies
then you have to ask whose T is it and
Well, all right, there is a
Right.
In particular, if you're looking at very
very distant galaxies
very distant galaxies when you look back
at them, you're looking back at them at
a time which is much earlier than your
local time.
And the question is then, should you use
the Hubble non-constant then or now?
Well, the answer is a combination of
both. But, when What But, um
This equation is at an instant of time.
It does not correspond to what you see
when you look back. All right, let's
let's let's talk about it. Since you
raised it, let's talk about it.
Let's draw a space-time diagram. Here's
time, here's space.
Now, here's the two points and they're
maintaining the same coordinate
positions. Nevertheless, the space is
expanding between them.
At a fixed instant of time, they're
separating with a velocity which is
related to the distance by the Hubble
constant at that instant of time.
But that's not what they see when they
look at each other. What they see when
they look at each other
is they look back
and they see one another
at an earlier time.
So, this fellow over here
sees this one moving away from him not
with the velocity that he has at the
same instant of time, but at the
velocity that he had at an earlier time.
And so, you have to use a more
complicated formula if you want to
answer the question of what somebody
sees. But, this is what is true at a
instant of time. At an instant of time,
this is true.
Okay.
Now, the fact that it's true is
may not be as interesting
as what you can actually detect by
looking back.
But, nevertheless, this correct formula.
Okay, now can the Hubble constant be
constant?
Is it something that is capable of
really just being a number and not
changing with time? Let's ask what it
says. Oh, no, before we do, let's let's
do something else.
Let's do something else. If this is true
that at any given instant of time at any
given instant of time that the velocity
is the distance times the Hubble
constant and space is infinite in every
direction and so forth then there is a
distance scale which is large enough
that things are moving away from you
with the speed of light. In fact,
there's a distance which is large enough
that they're moving away with from you
with 10 times the speed of light.
This is not a mistake.
This is a true statement that in
cosmology in an expanding universe like
this
two points two material points can be
moving away from each other with greater
than the speed of light.
They can't pass each other with greater
than the speed of light. If something
goes by you, it can't go by you faster
than the speed of light.
But
two things sufficiently far apart can
and the with the
the uh the relationship then between the
Hubble constant and the distance scale
in order that you are at the speed of
light, you would just get by putting in
C here.
C equals distance times H. And what it
tells you, C meaning the speed of light,
not the not some arbitrary constant
let's set the speed of light to one
as we usually do.
And then it would say at a distance
equal
to one over
the Hubble constant at that instant of
time, things in fact are moving away
from you at the speed of light.
Now, in most instances in most most
cosmologies
most I don't mean most cosmologies that
we used today, I mean in most
cosmologies that were studied in the
past
um
the Hubble constant decreased with time.
The Hubble constant decreased with time.
As time went on, the Hubble constant got
smaller and smaller.
Which meant that the distance out to
where things are moving with the speed
of light relative to you gets larger and
larger with time.
You might think if there's a
a galaxy out there which is moving away
from you with a speed of light or a
little more that you can never see it.
But, if the Hubble constant is
decreasing, you wait a little while and
you find out that the distance to which
you can see is larger.
In other words, the distance to where
things are moving with the speed of
light is larger.
And so
in most cosmologies
older cosmologies
it was the case that um
that there was no bound on what you
could eventually see.
The Hubble constant would get smaller
and smaller and smaller, so the distance
out to where the things were moving with
the speed of light would get larger and
larger and you would eventually see
them.
Modern cosmology, that's not the case.
Modern cosmology
the Hubble constant or the ultimate
Hubble constant
the ultimate Hubble constant meaning
ultimate in the future
appears as if it's becoming constant,
truly constant, constant with time.
Uh that's an observational fact.
I'm not going to tell you how We're not
getting into observational cosmology
here.
But, there is good evidence that we live
very strong evidence that we live in a
universe where the Hubble constant is
tending to a constant, a true constant.
So, let's investigate the consequences
of a universe in which the Hubble
constant is constant and ask what it's
like.
If it is the case
that the Hubble constant is a constant
then there is some universal distance
out to which
when you look out that distance, things
will be moving relative to you with the
speed of light and that distance won't
change with time.
All right, so let's let's investigate
that possibility. What does it say? What
does it mathematically say?
We're just going to spend a couple of
minutes out of tonight and then continue
next time. What it says, the Hubble
constant is A. over A.
A. of T over A of T equals H and that's
constant now.
Now, H is just a numerical constant. It
has some units. What are its units? One
over time. One over time, right?
Right.
So, when when you specify the Hubble
constant, you are specifying a time
scale.
In our universe, the relevant time scale
is about 12 about 15 billion years.
All right, so uh
the Hubble constant is a very small
number, but nevertheless, it appears to
be constant. Let's take it to be
constant. That says, let's rewrite this
equation. It says DA by DT
is equal to H times A.
Another way of saying that is that the
rate of change of something is
proportional to the thing itself. And
what is the solution of an equation like
that?
Exponential.
A
equals
A at some fixed time. Doesn't matter
what time. We We don't It's not even
important. Times E to the HT.
The scale factor increases
exponentially.
The distance between pairs of points
increases exponentially.
And that's called an inflating universe.
So, that's called
a space with this property. A space with
this property with A being of the form E
to 2 HT. Why did I put a two there?
Hm? It's squared. It is squared. A is E
to the HT. A squared is E to the 2 HT.
This space has a name. It's called a de
Sitter space. De Sitter space
through the um
uh the mathematical astronomer physicist
who first discovered it uh
de Sitter. I think Willem Willem de
Sitter.
Dutchman.
Small D small E
space
Sitter.
And
exponentially expanding.
Um
All right. I think we're going to I
think we're going to stop now. What I'm
going to show you next time is that de
Sitter spaces, spaces with this
property, have event horizons. Event
horizons which are in many respects
similar to black hole horizons.
Uh but they're almost like inside-out
horizons. When you think about a black
hole being outside the black hole
and looking at the horizon, you see a
region where things on the inside are
moving away from you faster than the
speed of light roughly. That's why they
can't get out.
Uh the horizon of de Sitter space is
quite the opposite. It's exactly the
opposite. A region out there at a large
enough distance where things are moving
away from you with the speed of light.
You're kind of on the inside of it and
things are moving away from you with the
speed of light
forever and ever. And then they You're
not going to And they You will never
catch up with them.
Passing through that horizon out there
where things are moving with the speed
of light, that's
as um
very similar to passing into the horizon
of a black hole.
The only difference is, as far as we
know, de Sitter space does not evaporate
like a black hole does.
Uh
So, we'll talk about de Sitter space.
We'll talk about its horizon.
And we'll talk about why it uh creates a
lot of confusion and interest in modern
cosmology.
For more, please visit us at
stanford.edu.